Finding Aid for the Lloyd E. Cotsen Cuneiform Tablets Collection LSC.1883
UCLA Library Special Collections
- School text, lexical exercise from OB Lu-Azlag D., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-11; 5 3/8" height x 4 1/8" width x 1" depth, rectangular multi-column tablet; Rectangular tablet of brown clay. There are three triangular gouges on the flat face most likely made with a modern tool: one is close to the center, this gouge is partially covered with an adhesive. There is a smaller triangular gouge on this face near another corner. This gouge is deep and it is unclear whether or not it was made while the clay was still wet or after the clay dried. Another, rougher gouge across an edge was most likely made with a modern tool. Some of the clay on this edge near this gouge has been scraped or pushed up from the convex face, most likely when the clay was still wet, so some pieces of clay extend out from that edge. There is another gouge across a different edge that is smoother with a patina similar to the rest of the tablet. This possibly could indicate this gouge was made when the clay was still wet. There is a large area on the flat face that looks worn away. There are some patches on the convex face that look to have been roughly scraped, possibly while the clay was still wet, based on the patina. There is a complete crack running from one side of the convex face across an edge. There is a white patch in one area on the convex face that looks like a thin layer of deposits. There are some white concretions visible throughout. (Drawer 5)
  This beginner's exercise is a student's vocabulary practice in writing descriptions of humans and human conditions (both mental and physical).
- School text, administrative exercise of year names., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 60; 5 3/8" height x 4 1/4" width x 1 1/8" depth, baked rectangular multi-column tablet; This tablet fragment was broken into three pieces and reattached using a clear adhesive. Two of the three pieces are corner pieces. Two corners are broken and lost. There is adhesive visible in the cracks where the three pieces were rejoined- there are some knotched losses at one side, and the flat edge of one corner is missing. Where the pieces were rejoined there are some deep holes, but they are small in diameter; these holes are the result of losses to the reattached pieces. The opposite face is mostly lost through spalling and is rough and uneven. The original surface of the tablet remains along one edge, where the inscription is retained. The tablet fragment appears to be coated with a glossy substance. A dark black substance is scattered on both faces. (Drawer 6)
  This basic student exercise allowed the scribe to practice writing the year names from the First Babylonian dynasty (c. 1894-1595 BCE). Based on the year names it is likely this tablet dates to Ammi-ditana, year 15 (c. 1670 BCE).
- School text, sign exercise., Old Akkadian- Ur III Period (c. 2340-2000 BCE); SC-I-2; 1. Lord; 2 1/16" height x 1 1/2" width x 9/16" depth, rectangular tablet with the reverse uninscribed; Rectangular tablet of grey-brown clay. The shape of the tablet is slightly irregular: two of the top corners were pressed in, most likely while the clay was wet. Another corner has a loss. There are incomplete cracks on the uninscribed face. The surface of the face is uneven with a few depressions, which were most likely made when the clay was still wet.
  This beginner's exercise is practicing writing the EN sign ("lord").
- School text, administrative exercise., Ur III Period (c. 2100-2000 BCE); SC-III-32; 1. n liters of cereal 2. 20 liters of cereal 3. 30 liters of barley 4. 10 liters of barley seed 5. 10 liters of black barley 6. 10 liters of green barley 7. 10 liters of … barley 8. 10 liters of cumin/barley of the thicket; 1 5/8" height x 1 5/8" width x 3/4" depth, square single column tablet with a deep circular impression on uninscribed reverse; Square tablet with a large, circular pit at the center of the uninscribed face. There are several incomplete cracks overall. There are minor surface losses and some white concretions visible overall. (Drawer 2)
  This student text contains a list quantities of cereals. Administrative texts are the most prevalent and popular type of ancient Mesopotamian text, so the scribe need ample practice to master this genre.
- School text, sign exercise from Syllable Alphabet A., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-II-1; (Syllabary--no translation); 4 3/4" height x 3 1/4" width x 1" depth, rectangular multi-column tablet joined from fragments with an ink mark "1"; Approximately 1/3 of the tablet has broken off and was reattached with clear adhesive; lumps of adhesive overfill some areas and are clearly visible on the surface of both faces. The edge of one face has a large gouge, apparently from a modern tool. This gouge continues onto part of the short side. The opposite face has a cluster of white spots near the repaired break. One edge near the corner has a small area of spalling. On the long side closest to the spalling there is a blue ink (?) mark "1 [inside a circle]". On one of the short sides opposite the gouge from the tool there is a white powdery spot. (Drawer 3)
- Letter with envelope from king Rim-Suen of Larsa., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-1h; 5" height x 2 1/4" width x 1 1/2" depth, rectangular single column tablet with the reverse uninscribed and an envelope partially preserved on the reverse; This rectangular tablet has a large fragment of envelop attached to one face; the clay of the envelop appears to have dried onto the tabet rather than being glued to it. About 1/3 of the face without the envelop fragment is lost to spalling. The area runs diagonally across the face. Cracks at either end of this part of the face are covered with clear adhesive. A crack in one corner away from the spalling is also covered with adhesive. Three of four corners have losses. The face with the envelop fragment has three large areas of adhesive. Two of these areas follow part of the outline of the envelop and continue onto one long side of the fragment. The third area covers a crack near the corner which continues onto the long side of the tablet. (This crack may actually be a break that was reattached.) A fourth, smaller, area of adhesive is on the other side of the face, continuing onto the long side of the tablet. All four corners have small losses. (Drawer 4)
  This royal letter is from king Rim-Suen to Suen-imguranni. Rim-Suen reigned from 1822-1763 BCE.
- School text, sign exercise., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 32; 1. Mouth 2. (Written by) 'The servant of Ninsun'; 3 1/2" diameter x 1 1/8" depth, red lentil with the reverse inscribed; Lenticular tablet fragment with large losses overall, particularly along the edges. Two of the area with losses have modern tool marks, indicating these losses are not ancient. There is one loss that may have occurred (at least partially) while the clay was still wet: there is a deep ditch on the convex face and the clay that has been pressed and pushed from this ditch forms a mound on the opposite face. Portions of both faces have some spalling, however, the losses are deeper on the convex face. There are some minor surface losses and incomplete cracks overall. A coating has been applied to the surface of the tablet. (Drawer 5)
  This beginner's exercise is a practice in sign formation and sound of the KA sign ("mouth"). The text is signed by its scribe, Ur-Ninsun.
- School text, mathematical exercise., Ur III Period (c. 2100-2000 BCE); PARS 93; 6 1/4" height x 3 1/4" width x 1" depth, large rectangular double column tablet joined from fragments; Tablet has been broken in two pieces repaired. Clay appears well fired. Adhesive is contained within damaged area. Surface is not coated. There appears to be mineral deposits (salts ?) vertically along one side. (Some adhesive may have darkened an area of the deposits). (Drawer 6)
  This basic student exercise allowed the scribe to practice writing the lists of morning and evening provisions for Ninlil's second shrine. This text is a duplicate of 96286.
- School text, legal exercise of a loan contract., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-24d; 4" height x 2 1/16" width x 5/8" depth, rectangular single column tablet joined from fragments; Rectangular tablet of grey-brown clay. The tablet has broken into two pieces. The two pieces have been reattached with an adhesive. The adhesive was also applied to the surface around the break. There are two complete and one incomplete cracks near one corner on which adhesive have also been applied. There are a few more incomplete cracks in the same area that are not covered with adhesive. There are some losses on the surface near the break as well as some small gaps caused by losses. There are some cream-colored concretions visible overall. (Drawer 1)
  This student practice contract is for a loan of silver from the king to Lu-Nanna in order to buy precious stones and prestige goods for the deity Ninsianna. The same personal names are used in 52176.
- School text, lexical exercise from Ura 1., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-24; Obverse 1. A door of date palm midribs 2. … 3. … 4. … 5. A doorpole 6. A crescent-shaped object on a door 7. The door handle 8. The door pivot Reverse 1. … 2. A bolt 3. … 4. A bolt 5. … 6. … 7. …; 2 7/8" height x 1 15/16" width x 13/16" depth, rectangular single column tablet joined from fragments; Rectangular tablet that has broken into two pieces. The two pieces have been reattached with adhesive. There is a jagged loss on the surface along the break line on one of the faces. On the other face, there is a gap where the two pieces have been reattached. This is possibly the result of the two pieces not being fit together properly when being reattached. (Drawer 2)
- School text, lexical exercise of personal names beginning with "ur"., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-5b; 1. 'Servant of new year' 2. 'Servant of the side' 3. 'Servant of the deity Damu'; 3 1/2" diameter x 1" depth, baked lentil joined from fragments with lines inscribed on reverse, but no writing; Lenticular tablet that split approximately in half but was reattached with opaque-white adhesive. One face has a deep incomplete crack running from the break at center out to the edge. There is an area of spalling at the edge where the second crack terminates. There is a small gouged loss at the edge of the tablet diagonally across from the spalling. The opposite face has a large gouged loss running next to the central reattached break. This loss is relatively recent, as it does not have the same patina as the rest of the tablet. Opaque-white adhesive is visible in the break. One edge of the tablet has a chipped loss; this loss has the same patina as the rest of the tablet. There is a small chipped loss at the edge of the tablet where the two broken pieces were reattached. (Drawer 3)
- School text, letter exercise with envelope., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-2b; 3 7/8" height x 2 1/8" width x 1 1/2" depth, rectangular single column tablet with two detached envelope fragments; A small rectangular tablet with two associated but detached envelop fragments. The tablet is relatively complete with only one small loss toward the edge of one face. The same face is blackened, possibly from burning. "b" is the larger envelop fragment, which has a negative impression of cuneiform symbols on its concave (interior) face. "c" is the smaller envelop fragment, which also has a negative impression on its interior. This fragment also has an incomplete crack. Both envelop fragments are quite fragile. (Drawer 4)
- School text, stylus exercise of a drawing of a goat and fish., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 74; 2 1/2" H x 4 3/8" W x 5/8" depth, rectangular tablet joined from fragments; Rectangular tablet that has broken into four pieces. These four pieces have been reattached with an adhesive. One of these pieces is near the corner and is a surface loss. There are some losses along portions of one of the breaks. There are notable losses on one edge along the two breaks that run across this edge. A coating appears to have been applied to the surface of the tablet. There are many incomplete cracks visible overall, particularly around existing breaks. There is one complete crack running over an edge. There are some minor losses such as chips and craters on the surface. It is possible some of these minor losses were created when the clay was still wet. (Drawer 5)
  This text was originally a student letter exercise on obverse, which was erased and replaced with drawing of a goat and fish. Part of the letter is still legible on the reverse.
- Administrative text for the sale of land., Early Dynastic III (c. 2600-2350 BCE); 201; Obverse C olumn 1 1. 10 iku, …, 2. 2 1/2 iku, the field of …; 3. 1 iku, the 'brick of the steppe country'; 4. 1 iku, the field of the 'houses of the dog'; 5. 1 iku, the field of the buru bird mound; Column 2 1. Ur-kusu 2. metal 3. he exchanged; 4. Kur-dadu 5. was its administrator; 6. 'Mother of the shrine'; 7. … 8. … Column 3 1. 'Servant of Gibil'; 2. … 3. 'House of going'; 4. 'Little pig', 5. a servant of Shara; 6. 'King of the festival', 7. the potter; 8. … 9. … Column 4 1. … 2. … 3. … 4. 'Servant of Gibil' 5. was its scribe; 6. (aforementioned names) were witnesses. Reverse Column 1 1. … 2 shekels of silver 2. 2 bronze 3. 2 shekels is its silver 4. 1 pretty thing 5. 1 … 6. The accounting official 'Going' was its scribe.; 3" height x 3 5/16" width x 1" depth, square multi-column tablet (Drawer 6)
- School text, legal exercise of a loan contract., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-24b; 3 5/8" height x 2" width x 15/16" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet with a loss along one short edge. On one face there are a few spots of clear adhesive filling cracks along this break. There is a shallow spot of spalling next to part of this adhesive. One the opposite face there are two smooth, diagonal gouges along the broken edge. These appear to be made by a strike from a modern tool because the clay here is a lighter color than the rest of the tablet. (Drawer 1)
  This tablet is a student practice writing a loan contract for silver. Note that the personal names the same as 52178.
- School text, mathematical exercise of a multiplication table., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-29; 3 1/2" height x 1 3/4" width x 1" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet of grey-brown clay. There are some losses on the surface of two of the corners and a small loss along one edge. There is adhesive on one of the corner losses. There is a cream-colored substance that has accumulated in many of the grooves of the cuneiform impressions. (Drawer 2)
  This tablet contains a multiplication table based on 15 with Old Babylonian sexagesimal notation.
- School text, lexical exercise from ugu-mu., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-39b; 4 3/16" height x 2 1/2" width x 15/16" depth, rectangular single column tablet joined from fragments with worn surfaces; Rectangular tablet fragment that has broken in three pieces. The pieces have been reattached with an adhesive. There are considerable losses along one edge of the tablet. as well as crevices due to losses at the breaks -- these crevices are particularly noticeable on the flat face. There is a slight gap at one of the breaks on the convex face, possibly indicating a misalignment when those pieces were reattached, or is the result of some losses from the break. There is a complete crack starting from the edge that runs about one inch diagonally cross the fragment. There is spalling on the surface of the losses. There is possibly some fill in this area too. There are minor losses to the surface of both faces. Small, white concretions are visible overall. The tablet is crumbling slightly. (Drawer 3)
- School text, administrative exercise of payments to workers., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 64; 5" height x 2 5/8" width x 1" depth, baked red rectangular single column tablet joined from fragments with an "X" across obverse; Rectangular, flat cuneiform tablet with an area of loss in one corner. On the face where that area of loss is larger, a thin piece of the surface has spalled off in two pieces. The pieces have been reattached with some small losses remaining, and adhesive is visible.This damage is most visible when the tablet is viewed in profile. The flatter end has a deep crack showing adhesive residue and a small crack, but the residue does not extend beyond the crack. The tablet appears coated with a glossy substance. All surfaces have scattered dark black marks.
  This student practice in writing administrative documents is dated to Samsu- ditana, year 14 of his reign (c. 1612). Samsu-ditana is the last king of the Old Babylonian dynasty.
- School text, administrative exericse of ration lists., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 121; 3 1/2" diameter x 13/16" depth, baked multi-column lentil joined from fragments; Lenticular tablet that was broken into three pieces and very inexpertly repaired. The tablet broke approximately in half, and then one small section broke off of one of the halves. The reattached pieces are badly misaligned, and a large amount of adhesive is applied within breaks and over much of the surface of both faces. On one face, the point where the smallest piece was reattached has a deep gouge on the interior edge; tiny fragments are visible but are heavily glued. A large, gouged crack/loss is at the edge of the tablet where part of the middle- sized reattached piece has been lost. On the largest reattached piece, there is a small deposit of a white-tan colored material near the edge furthest from the repaired breaks. The opposite face shows the same losses to the tablet overall that are described above. Even in the unbroken portion, a large quantity of adhesive covers the face and has run down to the edge of the tablet. A piece of white fiberous material is stuck in the adhesive. Some small, scattered areas on this face are dark gray and appear to be actually saturated with adhesive. There are two areas of tan-colored fill on this face: one is next to where the smallest broken piece is reattached, and the second area is just below the first.The color of the fill blends with the color of the actual clay of the tablet. (Drawer 5)
  This basic student practice text contains lists of rations distributed to workers as payment. This tablet has a very unusual layout.
- School text, literary exercise from a hymn to Nergal., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-13; 1. Nergal, 2. existing power being raised, 3. he shall stretch it out on the full land.; 2 3/8" height x 3 1/8" width x 7/8" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet with some losses at two of the corners. Near one of these corners on the convex face is another loss, a portion of which has been reattached with adhesive. The adhesive is also visible on a portion of the surface near the break. On this same side, there are minor chips to the surface. There is one larger chip near a corner. On the flat face (with cuneiform impressions) there are a few small losses and some surface abrasions. There is also a small, incomplete crack near one side, and a hole, possibly made by an implement near one corner. (Drawer 1)
  This advanced student practice is a praise to the underworld deity Nergal with no known parallel yet.
- School text, lexical exercise from Lu A., Uruk III (c. 3200-3000 BCE); SC-II-4b; (First two columns missing) Column 3 1. … 2. … 3. … 4. The chief … 5. The chief 6. … 7. … Column 4 1. The chief secretary 2. The linen secretary 3. … 4. … 5. The chief courtyard attendant 6. … 7. … Column 5 1. … 2. … 3. … 4. … 5. … 6. … 7. … 8. …; 3" height x 1 7/8" width x 5/8" depth, square multi-column fragment; Rectangular tablet fragment inscribed on one face only. The fragment has a diagonal break across one side. In about the middle of this diagonal break there is a small gouged loss. At the edge of the tabelt along the break there is a small area of spalling. On the intact side of the tablet there is a chipped loss at one corner. On the uninscribed face, the loss at the corner is larger and includes an area of spalling. At the edge of the tablet diagonally opposite the broken corner there is a smooth, slanted gouge/loss, possibly the result of a modern tool strike. About a half inch above this loss there is a small hole in the fragment. (Drawer 3)
- School text, letter exercise with envelope., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-2c; 4 1/8" height x 2" width x 1 3/16" depth, rectangular single column tablet with an envelope attached; Rectangular tablet fragment with one face almost completely covered by an envelop that has dried together with it. One large corner of both tablet and envelop is broken and lost. At one edge of this loss, a small fragment of envelop has a complete crack and is in danger of spalling. There are white deposits (salt?) along this crack that may be contributing to the danger. At one corner of the face without the envelop there is a gouge that continues onto the long side. A small piece of the side just below the gouge is cracked; this may actually be a reattached break. Near the corner diagonally opposite from the large loss is another gouge. On the enveloped face there is spalling (of face and envelop) connected to the large break. There is a large spot of a white deposit adjacent to the spalling. One edge of the envelop on a short side has a crack that runs the full length. (Drawer 4)
- School text, mathematical exercise in reciprocals., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 62; Obverse 1. n ~ 20 | 6 ~ 40 n 2. 3 ~ 30 […] (Remaining lines damaged) Reverse (Damaged); 3 1/2" height x 3 5/8" width x 3/4" depth, baked square tablet with the reverse destroyed; Tablet fragment that appears to be a portion of a rectangular tablet. One face is mostly intact, but the other face has been damaged by losses from spalling, leaving an uneven surface with varying thicknesses. A deep crack filled with adhesive runs down one side into the corner, where a deep chunk has been lost. Across from that crack is a small piece of white stone embedded in the clay. Both faces have scattered black/gray residue. The more damaged face appears to be coated with an unknown substance. The area around the deep crack is particularly glossy---this may be the same adhesive that is in the crack. (Drawer 5)
  This student text is a practice tablet of reciprocals of 16,000 (1/16,000). This tablet is a possible fake.
- School text., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-II-11; (Too damaged to reconstruct); 3 9/16" height x 2 3/4" width x 1" depth, irregular shape tablet with severely effaced surfaces; This tablet fragment is a portion of a rectangular tablet. One end has broken off unevenly. On the inscribed face, both corners opposite the broken end have small losses. The uninscribed face has a shallow pit and several hairline cracks; several of these areas have a white substance in them. Under magnification at least some of this white material is crystalline and appears to be salt. Additional spots of white crystalline material are scattered on the broken short end. (Drawer 3)